<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>

<!DOCTYPE rfc>

<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='rfc2629.xslt' ?>
<!-- used by XSLT processors -->
<!-- For a complete list and description of processing instructions (PIs),
     please see http://xml.resource.org/authoring/README.html. -->
<!-- Below are generally applicable Processing Instructions (PIs) that most I-Ds might want to use.
     (Here they are set differently than their defaults in xml2rfc v1.32) -->
<?rfc strict="yes" ?>
<!-- give errors regarding ID-nits and DTD validation -->
<!-- control the table of contents (ToC) -->
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<!-- generate a ToC -->
<?rfc tocdepth="4"?>
<!-- the number of levels of subsections in ToC. default: 3 -->
<!-- control references -->
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<!-- use symbolic references tags, i.e, [RFC2119] instead of [1] -->
<?rfc sortrefs="yes" ?>
<!-- sort the reference entries alphabetically -->
<!-- control vertical white space
     (using these PIs as follows is recommended by the RFC Editor) -->
<?rfc compact="yes" ?>
<!-- do not start each main section on a new page -->
<?rfc subcompact="no" ?>
<!-- keep one blank line between list items -->
<!-- end of list of popular I-D processing instructions -->

<rfc xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
        category="std" consensus="true"
        docName="draft-huque-dnsop-multi-alg-rules-00"
        ipr="trust200902"
        updates="4035,6840"
        obsoletes=""
        submissionType="IETF" xml:lang="en"
        tocInclude="true" tocDepth="4"
        symRefs="true" sortRefs="true" version="3">

  <!-- ***** FRONT MATTER ***** -->

  <front>
    <title abbrev="Multiple Algorithm Rules in DNSSEC">Multiple Algorithm Rules in DNSSEC</title>

    <author fullname="Shumon Huque" initials="S." surname="Huque">
      <organization>Salesforce</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>415 Mission Street, 3rd Floor</street>
          <city>San Francisco</city>
          <region>CA</region>
          <code>94105</code>
          <country>United States of America</country>
        </postal>
        <email>shuque@gmail.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Peter Thomassen" initials="P." surname="Thomassen">
      <organization>deSEC, SSE</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <city>Berlin</city>
          <country>Germany</country>
        </postal>
        <email>peter@desec.io</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <date day="10" month="7" year="2023"/>

    <!-- Meta-data Declarations -->

    <area>General</area>
    <workgroup>Internet Engineering Task Force</workgroup>
    <keyword>Internet-Draft</keyword>
    <keyword>DNS</keyword>
    <keyword>DNSSEC</keyword>
    <keyword>Multiple</keyword>
    <keyword>Algorithm</keyword>
    <keyword>Rules</keyword>

    <abstract>
      <t>
        This document proposes to address some limitations in the DNS
        protocol that pose challenges for configurations of multi-signer
        operation and for the transfer of signed DNS zones between providers,
        where the providers support disjoint DNSSEC algorithm sets.
      </t>
    </abstract>
  </front>

  <middle>

    <section title="Introduction and Motivation" anchor="intro">
      <t>
        RFC EDITOR: PLEASE REMOVE THE FOLLOWING PARAGRAPH BEFORE
        PUBLISHING: The source for this draft is maintained in GitHub
        at: https://github.com/shuque/draft-dnsop-multi-alg-rules
      </t>
      <t>
        The Domain Name System Security Extensions (DNSSEC)
        <xref target="RFC4033" /> <xref target="RFC4034" />
        <xref target="RFC4035" /> add data origin authentication
        and integrity protection to the Domain Name System (DNS),
        by having DNS zone owners (or their operators) crytographically
        sign their zone data.
      </t>
      <t>
        The <xref target="RFC8901">Multi-Signer Extensions</xref>
        describe how multiple providers using distinct DNSSEC keys can
        co-operatively serve the same DNS zone.
        <xref target="DNSSEC-AUTO">DNSSEC Automation</xref> further
        describes how to fully automate Multi-Signer operations, as well
        as how to use a transitional state of a multi-signer configuration
        to non-disruptively transfer a signed zone from one provider to
        another. These methods do not work however if the providers
        involved employ different DNSSEC algorithms, due to restrictions
        imposed by the current protocol specifications. This is not just
        a theoretical problem. Real situations in the field have occurred
        where this has posed an obstacle to DNSSEC deployment and
        operations.
      </t>
    </section>

    <section title="Current Multiple Algorithm Rules" anchor="multialg">
      <t>
        Section 2.2 (last paragraph) of <xref target="RFC4035" />
        states the following:
      </t>
      <t>
        "There MUST be an RRSIG for each RRset using at least one DNSKEY
         of each algorithm in the zone apex DNSKEY RRset. The apex DNSKEY
         RRset itself MUST be signed by each algorithm appearing in the DS
         RRset located at the delegating parent (if any)."
      </t>
      <t>
        Although unstated in that document, the original rationale for
        this rule was algorithm downgrade protection. An attacker cannot
        undetectably strip away signatures by a stronger algorithm from
        signed DNS responses.
      </t>
      <t>
        This rule cannot be satisfied if DNS providers deployed in a
        multi-signer configuration are using different signing algorithms.
        By extension, it also means that multi-signer techniques cannot
        be employed to non-disruptively transfer a signed zone from one
        DNS provider to another if the providers use differing algorithms.
      </t>
      <t>
        For online signers attempting to deploy multiple algorithms,
        this rule also imposes a significant computational burden,
        unless a selective algorithm negotiation mechanism is also
        developed.
      </t>
      <t>
        On the other hand, Section 5.11 of
        <xref target="RFC6840">DNSSEC Clarifications</xref> referring to
        the above rule states that:
      </t>
      <t>
        "This requirement applies to servers, not validators. Validators
        SHOULD accept any single valid path. They SHOULD NOT insist that all
        algorithms signaled in the DS RRset work, and they MUST NOT insist
        that all algorithms signaled in the DNSKEY RRset work."
      </t>
      <t>
        Effectively, this means that any validator following this rule
        does not provide algorithm downgrade protection, rendering the
        requirement in RFC 4035 somewhat meaningless. The two quoted
        assertions in RFC 4035 and 6840 are thus arguably contradictory.
      </t>
    </section>

    <section title="Support for a wide range of validators">

      <t>
        A secondary reason for the rule in RFC 4035 is that it
        allows signed data in the zone to be authenticatable by
        a wide range of validating resolvers that may support
        different algorithms. This is sound advice as a general
        rule, and allows a zone operator to introduce a newish
        algorithm that does not yet have wide support in the field
        by double signing it with a well known algorithm. But the
        rule is too rigid to support other reasonable configurations
        where differing algorithms may be in use, but all of which
        are very widely supported. Multi-signer and inter-provider
        transfers involving differing but only well known algorithms
        are cases in point.
      </t>
    </section>

    <section title="Does DNSSEC need algorithm downgrade protection?" anchor="downgrade">

      <t>
        All things being equal, algorithm downgrade protection would
        be a desirable property. But in general, only the zone owner
        knows the intent of their use of multiple algorithms. For example,
        if a zone owner wants to deploy a multi-signer configuration
        across two providers supporting the algorithms ECDSAP256SHA256
        and RSASHA256-3072-bit respectively, it should be possible to
        do so without unnecessary protocol impediments. Those algorithms
        are roughly comparable in strength and there is no threat of
        downgrade attack.
      </t>
      <t>
        More generally, a zone owner can avoid the threat of algorithm
        downgrade by simply choosing to use only a set of sufficiently
        strong algorithms. Validators should not unilaterally impose
        requirements that interfere with the zone owner's actual
        intentions. In fact, the clarifying behavior of validators in
        RFC6840 which states that they should accept "any" valid
        authentication path is compatible with this stance.
      </t>
      <t>
        The emerging threat of quantum computers may offer a more 
        compelling rationale for algorithm downgrade protection.
        A zone owner could double sign their zone with a classical
        as well as a post-quantum algorithm, and want to make sure a
        future break of the classical algorithm does not allow attackers
        to strip away the post quantum signatures. A secure signaling
        mechanism that permits a zone owner to advertise their intention
        in this regard would be useful. Note that presently no post
        quantum signature algorithms for DNSSEC have been standardized.
      </t>
    </section>

    <section title="Proposed Updates to RFCs" anchor="updates">
      <t>
        Initial proposal: relax the quoted rule in RFC 4035.
        Change the MUST to a SHOULD, and state that there are
        valid configurations where this rule could be disregarded.
      </t>
      <t>
        Longer term: develop a scheme to allow a zone owner to
        securely signal their desire for algorithm downgrade
        protection. One possible method to do this is a "DS hack":
        namely overloading the signed DS record set in the parent
        zone to convey this signal, a technique that has been met
        with some resistance by protocol purists in the past.
        Another method would be to define a new resource record type
        for this purpose. Special consideration would have to given
        to where such a signal would be placed for the root zone if
        needed (or whether the root zone should just have a hardcoded
        rule). Details of such a proposal are deferred to a future
        document (or a revision of this one). If and when such a
        proposal is developed, the text in RFC 6840, Section 5.11 will
        need to be updated to enforce algorithm downgrade protection
        in the presence of the signal.
      </t>
    </section>

    <section title="IANA Considerations" anchor="IANA">
      <t>
        Initially none. If a later scheme for algorithm downgrade
        signaling is developed, new protocol parameter numbers 
        will be needed for DS or a new resource record type.
      </t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="Security" title="Security Considerations">
      <t>
        TBD.
       </t>
    </section>

    <section title="Acknowledgements" anchor="acks">
      <t>
        The proposal in this draft was originally presented in
        <xref target="ICANN-TALK"/> by S. Huque at the ICANN73 DNSSEC
        and Security workshop.
      </t>
    </section>

  </middle>


  <!--  *****BACK MATTER ***** -->

  <back>

    <references title="Normative References">
        <xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4033.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4034.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4035.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6840.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8901.xml"/>
    </references>

    <references title="Informative References">
      <reference anchor="DNSSEC-AUTO"
                 target="https://www.ietf.org/archive/id/draft-ietf-dnsop-dnssec-automation-01.html">
        <front>
          <title>DNSSEC Automation</title>
          <author fullname="Ulrich Wisser" initials="U" surname="Wisser" />
          <author fullname="Shumon Huque" initials="S" surname="Huque" />
          <date />
        </front>
      </reference>
      <reference anchor="ICANN-TALK"
                 target="https://tinyurl.com/multisigner-rfc-adjustments">
        <front>
          <title>RFC Adjustments for Multi-Signer</title>
          <author fullname="Shumon Huque" initials="S" surname="Huque" />
          <date />
        </front>
      </reference>
    </references>

  </back>

</rfc>
